Guide to the Paul Apostolidis Interviews and Research Materials On Pasco Meatpacking Plant Workers
Special Collections, University of Washington Libraries
Paul Apostolidis interviews and research materials on Pasco meatpacking plant workers
1980-2006
1997-2006
University of Washington Libraries Special Collections Box 352900 Seattle, WA 98195-2900
6284
6284-001
Apostolidis, Paul,$d1965-
4.31 cubic feet 4 boxes
Interviews and research materials gathered by Apostolidis regarding immigrant meatpacking workers in Pasco, Washington
Paul Apostolidis teaches in the Government Department at the London School of Economics and Political Science in London, UK. Apostolidis was previously the T. Paul Chair of Political Science at Whitman College in Walla Walla, Washington where he taught classes on political theory and U.S. politics. His research focused on Latinx migrant laborers' work experiences, political organizations, and languages of collective action. His books include The Fight for Time: Migrant Day Laborers and the Politics of Precarity (Oxford University Press, 2019), Breaks in the Chain: What Immigrant Workers Can Teach America about Democracy (University of Minnesota Press, 2010), and Stations of the Cross: Adorno and Christian Right Radio (Duke University Press, 2000). Paul is co-editor of Public Affairs: Politics in the Age of Sex Scandals (Duke University Press, 2005). His current research explores neoliberal power relations via an analysis of work experiences and political organizing among migrant day laborers.
Collection is currently arranged as it was received upon donation, divided into the following two series:
SERIES 1: PAPERS
SERIES 2: AUDIOVISUAL MATERIAL
The collection contains interviews and research materials created and gathered by Paul Apostolidis which formed the basis for his 2010 book Breaks in the Chain: What Immigrant Workers Can Teach America about Democracy.
Paper-based research materials include print transcriptions, newspaper articles, scholarly papers, materials from courses taught by Apostolidis at Whitman College, legal records, and correspondence with Teamsters, Tyson, and research team members.
Audiovisual material consists primarily of original recordings on audiocassettes and minicassettes of about 40 interviews with immigrant meatpacking workers in Pasco who were members of International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Local 556 (the local represented workers at the Tyson/IBP beef plant in Wallula, WA just outside Pasco; in 2005, Tyson destroyed the union through company-engineered decertification elections). Other audiovisual materials include VHS tapes, a DVD of news coverage, and depositions of employees.
Forms part of the Labor Archives of Washington.
No restrictions on access for paper-based materials; however, no user access copy is currently available for VHS tapes and audiocassette. Users may obtain a reproduction of the media for a fee by contacting Special Collections.
Access to VHS tapes and interview audiocassette is restricted. An appointment with the Labor Archives curator is required prior to viewing. Contact UW Special Collections for more details or to request an appointment.
Donated by Paul Apostolidis.
Apostolidis, Paul. 2010. Breaks in the Chain: What Immigrant Workers Can Teach America About Democracy. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press.
Apostolidis, Paul,$d1965-$vArchives; Breaks in the chain$vSources; International Brotherhood of Teamsters.$bLocal 556 (Pasco, Wash.)$xHistory$vSources; Tyson (Firm)$xHistory$vSources; Tyson (Firm)$xEmployees$xHistory$vSources; Meat industry and trade$zWashington (State)$zPasco$xHistory$vSources; Packing-house workers$zWashington (State)$zPasco$xHistory$vSources; Packing-house workers$xLabor unions$zWashington (State)$zPasco$xHistory$vSources; Packing-houses$zWashington (State)$zPasco$xHistory$vSources; Labor$zWashington (State)$zPasco$xHistory$vSources; Labor unions$zWashington (State)$zPasco$xHistory$vSources; Labor movement$zWashington (State)$zPasco$xHistory$vSources; Course materials; Law materials; Business correspondence; Interviews; Newspaper clippings; Labor Archives of Washington (University of Washington); Personal Papers/Corporate Records; Labor History; Labor Unions; Washington (State); Sound Recordings
- SERIES 1: PAPERS, 1990-2006; 1997-2006
  - Letters: Martinez et al vs. International Brotherhood of Teamsters, 1999 November 2-2000 April 3 (Box-folder 1/1)
    References David Mark, James P. Hoffa, and Allen Hobart
  - Letters, notices, handwritten ballot counts, news articles: Wallula, WA strike and boycott, 1999 June 28-2000 March 3 (Box-folder 1/2-1/4)
    Includes information about Teamsters Local 556 vs. IBP, Inc. (Joint Council of Teamsters, JC-28, Food Processing Division)
  - "Pasco 200 Years in the Making," Ben Sadler and Alison Wallisch (brief history of events from 1805-2003), 2004 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Voting behavior in Franklin County, Washington (from election data, 1989-2003), 2004 October 29 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Demographic Analysis: Columbia and Benton Counties (1990 and 2000) with brief note to reader, census data, 1990-2000 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Local candidates for Franklin County: candidate interviews, receipts and expenditures, registration forms, 2004 October 29 (Box-folder 1/8)
    References Griffith, Johnson, and Vaux
  - United States naturalization and citizenship training information, approximately 2004 (Box-folder 1/9)
    Includes Whitman College politics resource guide, INS examination, test questions, instructions, and requirements
  - "Greasing the Wheels of Pork Barrel Politics," Max Hensley, Kyle Krohn, 2004 October 29 (Box-folder 1/10)
  - The Race to the Finish: Federal Election Candidates 2004: US Campaigns and Elections, Whitman College, 2004 October 27 (Box-folder 1/11)
  - "Political Activity among Latinos in Pasco, Washington: A Case Study in Power", thesis by Matthew P. Osdol, 2004 April 20 (Box-folder 1/12)
  - Final Report of the Community-Based Learning Partnership, 2002 December 8 (Box-folder 1/13-1/17)
    Includes transcripts of IBP worker interviews on occupational safety and health problems, light duty experiences, and food safety and corporate research on Tyson/IBP
  - University of Oregon, Effective Joint Labor-Management Health and Safety Committees, 2002 September (Box-folder 1/18)
  - LERC (Labor Education and Research Center), University of Oregon: Training materials in Spanish, 2002 (Box-folder 1/19)
  - Poultry Worker Justice Legal Advocacy Conference, Nashville, Tennessee, 2001 November (Box-folder 1/20)
  - Memorandum, Law Office of David N. Mark: Teamster trusteeship document production, Local 556 membership meetings, 1999 March 29 - July 28 (Box-folder 1/21-1/22)
  - Local 556: complaint sheets, notices, newsletters, news articles, 2000 September 22-2002 October 1 (Box-folder 1/23)
  - Teamsters Local 556: handwritten notes, letters, newspaper articles, approximately 2001-2002 (Box-folder 1/24)
    Includes issue of Spanish language Teamster newspaper ¡Adelante! and Su Periódico La Voz
  - Final Report of the Community-Based Learning Partnership, 2002 December 8 (Box-folder 1/25-1/26)
    Includes transcript of IBP worker interviews on occupational safety and health problems, light duty experiences, and food safety. Prepared for Teamsters Local 556 by Students in Paul Apostolidis' Politics 313 course at Whitman College.
  - Final report of the Whitman College/Teamsters Local 556 Community Partnership: research on Tyson Fresh Meats, Incorporated and Smith Frozen Foods, 2004 May (Box-folder 2/1-2/3)
    Includes Apostolidis' Politics 313 Course Introduction, Latina Policy and Issues Brief, Tyson wages handout, and 2 short student papers on health and safety and consumer advocacy
  - Teamsters Local 556/Tyson Fresh Meats: flyers, other communication regarding health care cost changes, 2004 (Box-folder 2/4)
  - Teamsters Local 556 contract proposals to Tyson Fresh Meats, Pasco, Washington, 2004 (Box-folder 2/5)
  - International Brotherhood of Teamsters Research Department Agreement Summary Report, 1997 November 10-2006 February 25 (Box-folder 2/6)
    Contains information on EXCEL Corporation, IBP Inc., and bargaining agreement between Smith Frozen Foods and Teamsters Local 556
  - International Brotherhood of Teamsters: election letters, hearing documents, flyer, news item regarding dispute of Maria Martinez and Maria Sauceda vs. Allen Hobart, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 2/7)
  - Land title of Walla Walla County property inquiry: Teamsters Local 556 property at 1750 Portland Ave., Walla Walla, Washington, 2004 February 4 (Box-folder 2/8)
  - Order from Chief United States District Judge, Eastern District of Washington: Maria Martinez and Maria Sauceda vs. International Brotherhood of Teamsters, 2000 March 3 (Box-folder 2/9)
  - Copies of letters, petitions regarding Martinez vs. the International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Local 556: Fax transmissions from Ken Pedersen to David N. Mark, 2000 January 14 (Box-folder 2/10)
  - General Teamsters, Warehousemen, and Cannery Workers, Local Union 556: consolidated financial statement, 1998 December 31 (Box-folder 2/11)
  - Meeting with members of Local 556: International Brotherhood of Teamsters, AFL-CIO, Pasco, Washington, 1999 August 9 (Box-folder 2/12)
  - Teamsters Local 556, Walla Walla, WA: Legal documents, Trustee's reports, labor organization reports, 1997-1999 (Box-folder 2/13)
  - Local 556 Communication: letters, depositions, statement of assets and liabilities, copy of settlement agreement regarding Martinez et. al v. the International Brotherhood of Teamsters, 1998 June 16-2000 August 21 (Box-folder 2/14)
  - Trusteeship 0556: petitions in support, letters, and information requests (07/12/1999), 1999 July-2000 January (Box-folder 2/15)
  - Color photographs: Teamsters Local 556, approximately 2000 (Box-folder 2/16)
  - Meatpacking Industry Workers Bill of Rights, 2000 July 27- 2004 June 30 (Box-folder 2/17)
    Includes letter from Governor Johanns
  - Research Education Advocacy People (REAP) General Profile on Tyson Foods, Inc. and IBP, Inc., 2001 December (Box-folder 2/18)
  - Letter from Rick Bender, President of Washington State Labor Council, opposing ballot measures, 2003 April 21 (Box-folder 2/19)
    Includes flyers concerning Initiatives 807 (to reimpose state spending limits) and 841 (to impose new supermajority requirement for tax increases or repealing business tax breaks)
  - Organizing to Win Strong Contracts, TDU Annual Convention, Detroit, Michigan: printed materials and notes, 2003 October 26 (Box-folder 2/20)
  - Teamsters Local 556: letters from Maria Martinez supporting contract bargaining, proposal list, copies of supporting published articles, 1998-2004 (Box-folder 2/21)
  - Tyson Foods and Jefferson Strike: flyer and articles, 2000-2003 (Box-folder 2/22)
  - "Road to Freedom" Tri-City Herald article, 2003 September 24 (Box-folder 2/23)
    Relates to Freedom Ride from Seattle to Washington, D.C. to draw attention to Civil Rights issues faced by immigrants
  - Meeting with Walla Walla community, Walla Walla Community College and Alliance for Workplace Justice, 2003-2005 (Box-folder 2/24)
    Includes materials from Whitman/Community Forums and related organizing items as well as agendas, news articles, feedback letter from Paul Apostolidis, follow-up articles, flyers, and notes
  - Teamsters Local 556: letters, articles calling for support for local 556 workers, including outreach to Japanese workers and consumers, 2004 June 24-July 31 (Box-folder 2/25)
  - One Million Voices Campaign materials on immigrant workers' rights, 2002 (Box-folder 2/26)
  - Paul Apostolidis documents: letters and writings concerning Local 556 decertification election, 2004 March 11-2005 February 25 (Box-folder 2/27)
  - Agreement summary reports/ food processing: pay schedules, job brackets, 1997-2006 (Box-folder 2/28)
    References Great Bend Meat Packing, Excel Corporation, Clougherty Packing Company, and IBP, Inc.
  - Evaluation of worker health and safety, food safety, and humane slaughter at the Tyson Fresh Meats Plant in Pasco, Washington, 2005 January 28 (Box-folder 2/29)
    Includes English and Spanish surveys for workers.
  - Work safety, food processing, wages, and Initiative 841: news items, articles, flyers, 2003-2004 (Box-folder 2/30)
  - Tyson and Meatpacking news clippings, 1998 May 22-2007 March 18 (Box-folder 2/31)
  - Safe Works/Safe Food: incorporation documents, minutes, supporting documents and letters, 2004 June 4 - August 4 (Box-folder 2/32)
  - Immigrant Workers Freedom Ride: news clippings, 2003 September 17-October 6 (Box-folder 2/33)
  - Immigrant Workers Freedom Ride: news clippings, color photographs, 2003 September (Box-folder 2/34)
  - Immigrant Workers Freedom Ride: organizing materials, 2003-2004 (Box-folder 2/35)
  - Immigrant Workers Freedom Ride: Media packet and handouts, IWFR, Walla Walla, 2003 September (Box-folder 2/36)
  - Labor Notes newspaper issues, 2001 November-2002 December (Box-folder 2/37)
  - Newspaper articles reporting labor issues, 1999 June 7-2006 April 17 (Box-folder 2/38)
  - Campaign materials, Teamsters Local 556, approximately 2001-2003 (Box-folder 2/39)
  - Labor Agreements, Teamsters Local 556, with IBP, Inc. and Lamb-Weston, 1999 July 8-2002 April 1 (Box-folder 2/40)
    Includes legal declaration supporting Maria Ramirez and Maria Saucedo.
- SERIES 2: AUDIOVISUAL MATERIAL, 1980-2005
  - John Carter Deposition (3 VHS Tapes), 2000 January 10 (Box 3)
    Access Restricted
  - Al Hobart Deposition (3 VHS tapes), 2000 January 11 (Box 3)
  - "Can't Take No More", U.S. Department of Labor (VHS Tape), 1981 (Box 3)
  - "Safety Pays" (VHS Tape), approximately 1980-2000 (Box 3)
  - "The Prophetic Witness", National Interfaith Committee for Worker Justice (VHS Tape), 2002 (Box 3)
  - NOW with Bill Moyers. Tyson Strike (VHS Tape), 2003 (Box 3)
  - "Get On the Bus": Remarks by Dr. Bennie Mitchell, National Baptist Convention - USA, Inc. to the United Food and Commercial Workers International Union 5th Regular Convention (VHS Tape), 2003 August 1 (Box 3)
  - Tyson Fresh Meats, Inc., Un Mensaje Importante para usted y su familia, "Una Trayectoriia Nueva Junto" (VHS Tape), approximately 2002 - 2003 (Box 3)
  - "Tyson 'No'" (DVD), approximately 2002-2005 (Box 4)
  - Teamsters Local 556 Migrant Worker Interview Audio Recordings, 2002-2005 (Box 4)